Christopher Schmidt-Nowara Papers MS230
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Christopher Schmidt-Nowara Papers
2011 -- 2015
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS230
1.2 Linear Feet
7 Digital Object(s) 7 digital objects containing 140 files.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Tufts University Department of History, 2017, accession MS-2018-040.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: Additional accessions, and 2018 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
Christopher Schmidt-Nowara (1966-2015) was a professor of history at Tufts University from 2011 until his death in 2015.
Christopher Schmidt-Nowara was born in Cleveland, Ohio, on September 6, 1966, to Wolfgang Schmidt-Nowara, MD, and Elizabeth Ebert Schmidt-Nowara. After graduating from the Albuquerque Academy in 1984, Christopher Schmidt-Nowara went to Kenyon College, where he earned his BA in 1988. He then pursued his doctoral work at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor under the direction of Rebecca Scott and Geoff Eley. During this time he was both a Mellon fellow and a Fulbright recipient. He completed his Ph.D. in 1995.
Before coming to Tufts University in 2011, Schmidt-Nowara was a Magis Distinguished Professor and associate chair of the history department at Fordham University in New York. He also taught at Standford, University of Puerto Rico, the University of São Paulo, Princeton, and the Fernand Braudal Center in Binghamton. In 2011 Schmidt-Nowara joined the Tufts faculty as a professor of history and the third holder of the Prince of Asturias Chair of Spanish Culture and Civilization.
Schmidt-Nowara's research examined slavery, emancipation, colonialism, and nationalism in Spain's Atlantic empire and Latin American during the nineteenth century. His many publications include the books Empire and Antislavery: Spain, Cuba, and Puerto Rico, 1833-1874 (1999), The Conquest of History: Spanish Colonialism and National Histories in the Nineteenth Century (2006),and Slavery, Freedom and Abolition in Latin America and the Atlantic World (2011). At the time of his death he was working on an edited version of Lieutenant Fernando Blanco White's account of his escape from captivity during the Napoleonic era. The manuscript is entitled Flight to Freedom: A Spanish Prisoner in Napoleon's Europe, 1814.
Christopher Schmidt-Nowara had a daughter named Althea Rose Spieler-Nowara with Miranda Spieler in 2011. On June 27, 2015 after a short illness, Schimdt-Nowara died in Paris, France.
Custodial History
In October 2015, Margaret Peachy, Digital Archivist, retrieved Schmidt-Nowara's digital files from his computer in the Department of History. In December 2015, Molly Schmidt Nowara, sister of Christopher, donated one box of his teaching and research files.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of teaching and research files including Schmidt-Nowara's correspondence, CV, faculty information form, course files, readings, conference and research notes, and travel files. This collection also contains a 2013 class notebook beloging to Nowara; a book manuscript for LSU Press titled "Flight to Freedom"; a memory book created by the Tufts University Department of History titled "For Althea"; and the contents of a flash drive containing various MS word, powerpoint, and image files related to lectures by Nowara and his research.
Schmidt-Nowara, Christopher; Imperialism--History--19th century; Slavery--Latin America--History; Faculty papers; Teaching and learning
- Additional accessions, 2011 -- 2015; MS230.001; 3.6 Linear Feet; 3 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of teaching and research files including Schmidt-Nowara's correspondence, CV, faculty information form, course files, readings, conference and research notes, and travel files.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation. Open for research.
  - Desktop folder, 2011 -- 2015; MS230-001
    Open for research.
  - Documents folder, 2011 -- 2015; MS230-002
  - Travel drive, 2011 -- 2015; MS230-003
  - Teaching and research files, 2011 -- 2015; MS230-004 (Box 1)
    75 years from the date of creation.
    CV, faculty information form, course files, readings, conference and research notes, and student papers.
- 2018 accessions, circa 2013 -- 2015; MS230.002; 3 Folder(s); 4 Digital Object(s) 4 digital objects containing 137 files.
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by the Tufts University Department of History, 2017, accession MS-2018-040.
  This series contains a 2013 class notebook beloging to Nowara; a book manuscript for LSU Press titled "Flight to Freedom"; a memory book created by the Tufts University Department of History titled "For Althea"; and the contents of a flash drive containing various MS word, powerpoint, and image files related to lectures by Nowara and his research.
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This series/sub-series may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
  - Class notebook, 2013; MS230.002.001.00041; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Book manuscript: "Flight to Freedom", circa 2015; MS230.002.001.00042; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Department of History memory book: "For Althea", 2015; MS230.002.001.00043; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Kew research, 2014; MS230.002.00001; 134 Digital Object(s); 501.6 Megabytes
  - Revolution and Reaction in Spain, 2014; MS230.002.00002; 1 Digital Object(s); 0.1 Megabytes
    MFA lecture text
  - Schmidt Nowara MFA lecture, 2014; MS230.002.00003; 1 Digital Object(s); 47.8 Megabytes
    MFA lecture images
  - Transition from slavery to freedom Nantes, 2015; MS230.002.00004; 1 Digital Object(s); 32.7 Megabytes
    Lecture at Université de Nantes